Jonah 1
Now the word of the LORD came unto Jonah the son of Amittai, saying,
Arise, go to Nineveh, that great city, and cry against it;
for their wickedness is come up before me.
But Jonah rose up to flee unto Tarshish from the presence of the LORD,
and went down to Joppa; and he found a ship going to Tarshish:
so he paid the fare thereof, and went down into it, to go with them unto Tarshish from the presence of the LORD.
That is quite an attempt to escape God.
Jonah is supposed to go to Nineveh, somewhere in Northern Iraq.
He is at Joppa near the current Tel Aviv and is about to sail somewhere in Spain.
As far as possible, to the westernmost place of the known word those days.
But the LORD sent out a great wind into the sea, and there was a mighty tempest in the sea, so that the ship was like to be broken.
Then the mariners were afraid, and cried every man unto his god,
So those mariners had different gods.
Or let's say that
the fact whether or not they worshipped the LORD isn't made absolutely clear.
It's safe to interpret that at least some of them served a false god at that point
which they called upon.
and cast forth the wares that were in the ship into the sea, to lighten it of them.
But Jonah was gone down into the sides of the ship; and he lay, and was fast asleep.
So the shipmaster came to him, and said unto him, What meanest thou, O sleeper?
arise, call upon thy God, if so be that God will think upon us, that we perish not.
Does that ring any bells?
Christ is sleeping on the boat
and there came down a storm of wind on the lake; and they were filled with water, and were in jeopardy.
And they came to him, and awoke him, saying, Master, master, we perish.
Then he arose, and rebuked the wind and the raging of the water: and they ceased, and there was a calm.
Sleeping Jonah resembles Christ at least a bit.
He clearly isn't Christ, but still he
seems like a distant echo for what's coming in the future with Christ.
And they said every one to his fellow,
Come, and let us cast lots, that we may know for whose cause this evil is upon us.
So they cast lots, and the lot fell upon Jonah.
Then said they unto him, Tell us, we pray thee, for whose cause this evil is upon us;
What is thine occupation? and whence comest thou? what is thy country? and of what people art thou?
And he said unto them, I am an Hebrew; and I fear the LORD, the God of heaven, which hath made the sea and the dry land.
Then were the men exceedingly afraid, and said unto him, Why hast thou done this?
For the men knew that he fled from the presence of the LORD, because he had told them.
Then we get into a situation where Jonah resembles surprisingly much Christ Himself.
Then said they unto him, What shall we do unto thee, that the sea may be calm unto us?
for the sea wrought, and was tempestuous.
And he said unto them, Take me up, and cast me forth into the sea; so shall the sea be calm unto you:
for I know that for my sake this great tempest is upon you.
It's almost as if Christ would say: take and crucify me on the cross.
He doesn't say that, but He nevertheless accepts that.
And that's where the storm of God's anger is calmed.
Nevertheless the men rowed hard to bring it to the land;
This is what the men usually do to the last. Establish their own works in order to please God.
but they could not: for the sea wrought, and was tempestuous against them.
There was a greter force which couldn't be resisted.
Wherefore they cried unto the LORD, and said, We beseech thee, O LORD, we beseech thee, let us not perish for this man's life,
and lay not upon us innocent blood:
— "Lay not upon us innocent blood!"
for thou, O LORD, hast done as it pleased thee.
This resembles Christ hanging on the cross a lot:
Now when the centurion saw what was done, he glorified God, saying, Certainly this was a righteous man.
And all the people that came together to that sight,
beholding the things which were done, smote their breasts, and returned.
So they took up Jonah, and cast him forth into the sea: and the sea ceased from her raging.
Then the men feared the LORD exceedingly, and offered a sacrifice unto the LORD, and made vows.
In Jonah we have a very much Christ like prophet.
Jonah is thrown away from the ship in order for the rest of the people to be saved.
Likewise Christ is crucified on the cross for our sake in order us to be saved.
In so many ways this Old Testament text refers to Christ our Lord.
And especially Christ crucified!
For they say: lay not upon us innocent blood.
That's exactly what made peace on the cross.
— The Son of Man's innocent blood given for us on the cross.
This is a very nice text.
We'll continue on the second chapter soon.